so health is arguably the single
most important area of our life
without our health
we can have all the money in the world
the best career the best relationships
the most fun hobbies and we won't be able to enjoy any of them
because our health is miserable
but even though we might know intellectually
that our health is important
when it comes to how we spend our time
it's often the first thing that goes
work are life gets busy
and the first thing we do is we stop sleeping properly
we stop eating well we stop exercising
because who's got time for those things
now as a former doctor turned entrepreneur and productivity expert
I've been on a missiono recently
to apply the principles of productivity
to my health and fitness and wellbeing
so I've been reading a bunch of books about health
working with an online health coach
and interviewing a bunch of experts on my podcast
all about physical health mental health and even emotional health
but a lot of the stuff that I've learned can be pretty dense
so I've been trying my best to translate
the things that I've Learned into simple
actionable evidence based hacks
that can seamlessly integrate into my life
so that the important aspects of my health are an autopilot
so I don't have to think too hard about them
and so in the video
I want to share 8 of these health hacks that have improved my life
and I hope you'll find something to take away from these
that you can apply to your life as well
now according to the CDC
1 and 3 adults in the US report
not getting enough sleep and not getting enough rest in the day
I suspect the actual number is higher than this
because I very rarely meet people
who feel as if they get enough sleep
now one simple hack that I found for improving my sleep
in a very easy to remember way
is the 3 2 1 method
which comes from my online fitness coach Dan Go
so the 3 in the method means
to stop eating three hours before sleeping
this study for example showed that
eating within 3 hours of your normal bedtime
was associated with nocturnal awakening
which basically means that you're waking up at night
and so your sleep quality is reduced
so that was the 3
then we have the 2
which is to stop drinking liquids two hours before sleep
you might know that drinking caffeine in the evening
is likely to disrupt your sleep
but actually drinking any kind of fluid even water
one to two hours before sleeping
has been associated with lower sleep quality as well
and then the 1 is to
cut out screen usage
1 hour before sleeping
and again there's a bunch of studies that show
that if you look at a bright screen
one hour before sleeping
that's likely to affect your sleep quality
especially when it comes to phones and stuff
the overstimulation that we get from our phones
which is literally what our phones are designed to do
is something that can make falling asleep
a lot harder than it necessarily needs to be
so the way that I personally combat this
is that I try my best to just not use my phone in bed
and instead I have a Kindle and
also a physical book on my bedside table
there was a study that showed
that the backlight from a Kindle
doesn't really affect sleep very much
and I find that generally my sleep is better
if I'm reading fiction rather than non fiction
fiction helps my brain switch off
it helps immerse myself in a new fantasy land and stuff
whereas nonfiction when I'm reading it in bed
I'm always thinking about my business and highlighting stuff
I feel the need to take notes
and it's stimulating my brain
in a way that fiction really doesn't
all right so I've got this graph from 2020
and this shows how many steps on average
I was taking each month
and you can see over here in August 2020
there is a significant dip
and this was when I first took a break
from my full time job of being a doctor
I ended up sitting on this desk all day
making YouTube videos
now this is a graph of my body weight
and you can see that there is a fantastic correlation
between when I stopped taking all these steps
and suddenly my weight absolutely ballooned
and I became pretty fat
so if you're watching this video
you probably have a job where you sit down all day
and you've heard this before
sitting is the new smoking
and they've done so many studies about this
where basically they show that physical inactivity
is this golden bullet that just
increases your risk of dying from all sorts of bad things
and as you might have heard
taking 10000+ steps per day
is generally a very good thing
this meta analysis of 15 studies for example
show that taking more steps per day
was associated with a progressively lower risk of
all cause mortality
this study showed that in sedentary overweight individuals
10000 steps a day significantly lower their anxiety depression
anger fatigue confusion and total mood distress
in this study for example
showed that for every 500 steps you increase per day
the risk of cardiovascular disease
decreases by about 6%
and so what I've tried to do is
add as many simple hacks to my life
to get to my 10,000 steps a day goal
so firstly the single best thing that I found for this
is actually to get a treadmill
underneath my standing desk
it was about $300 but it was totally worth it
it's the WalkingPad C2
I have no relationship with them at all but
I would recommend you can check it out
I've had this treadmill under my desk for a few months
I've used it 148 times
and walked 255km in that time
in fact today according to my Apple Watch
Iv'e racked up about 5000 steps already
and I haven't really left the house
so the treadmill has been a surprisingly simple hack
that has actually let me get in more the steps each day
secondly wherever possible
i like to take a zoom call while I'm walking
thirdly if I have to go somewhere for dinner or something
and it's within about 40 minutes of where I live
I'll often choose to walk
rather than drive or take the train
and usually while I'm walking I listen to podcast or something
but again you just gets the steps in
because 40 minutes there and back
basically gets me to about 10000 steps
and it's just been helpful to monitor it with my apple watch
you can do this with basically any phone
you don't need a smart watch
but any phone has a step counter in it as well
so if you have a phone in your pocket
you can see how many steps you've done
and since becoming conscious of the fact
that I'm trying to get 10000 steps a day
I have increased my step count each day
ok so earlier this year I got a bunch of blood tests done
and then when the doctor was kind of
talking me through the results afterwards
he asked if I have a particularly stressful job
and I said well no I don't really have a stressful job
I just sit around making YouTube videos
and then he said okay but has anyone around you
ever said that you need to take a break
and I was like yeah
everyone around me tells me I need to take a break
and he was like I thought so
because your stress markers are elevated
and that is really bad for someone of your age
I was like wait what stress markers are elevated
I don't feel stressed
I don't feel like I have a particularly stressful job
but then I look at my calendar
and it's like back to back
one thing to another to another to another to another
and this whole like running your own business thing
I thought it would give me more free time
than kind of working in medicine
but it actually gave me a lot less free time
than working in medicine
and there is that nice quote which is that you know
entrepreneurs work 60 hours a week
to avoid having to work 40 hours a week
I think that's very true
and again chances are if you're watching this channel
I suspect your stress levels are high as well
because you're probably busy
you'd like to be productive
you've got lots of things going on
and what the doctor said is that I should meditate more
and I was like meditation who cares
but then I saw some studies
and those studies show that if you meditate
it reduces your blood pressure
it reduces your cortisol levels
which is a stress hormone
it reduces your heart rate
reduces your cytokine levels
which is a Mark of inflammation
it can also increase your self compassion
and your attention and your focus
and so there's just like a mountain of evidence
saying that meditation is good for you
so I was like ok fine I'll do some meditation
and then I thought OK what app should I use for meditation
because obviously I want it to be easy and obviously
the name headspace came to mind
because they basically dominate the space
and so we reached out to them
and they very kindly agreed to sponsor this video
so thank you headspace for sponsoring this video
headspace is great
I've slowly working my way through the introductory course
and it's nice cuz you can choose different voices
to guide you through the meditation
and doing just a five to ten minute meditation
the first thing in the morning
before I do my journaling and before I get my coffee
I've actually been finding it really helpful
one thing that it does is that
it helps me kind of connect to the here and now a little bit more
is like you're closing your eyes
you're imagining like
experiencing the sounds of nature around you
or whatever that might be
and it's just like a moment of respite
before the craziness of the day starts
and it's becomes something I look forward to
after I have my shower
I have a hot shower then I turn it to cold
then I get changed and then I'm like cool
five to ten minutes
I can definitely find time to do
five to ten minutes of meditation on headspace
the other cool thing about headspace is that
it's very non judgmental
they basically say that there's no
right or wrong approach to meditation and mindfulness
you can do whatever works for you
and everyone seems to have a different routine
a different frequency
a different favorite type of content
and that's totally fine
now if you're interested in trying out meditation
and you want to use headspace
you can use the QR code on screen
and that will let you sign up for a completely free 60 day trial
so you can literally try it every day for two months
and you can see if you vibe with it
I've been vibing with it so much
that I now pay the monthly subscription for headspace
and it's totally worth it
so if you'd like to give it a go you can try it out
you can see if you like it
and you'd also be supporting the channel as well
so thank you so much headspace
for sponsoring this video
okay this is a really cool one
this is a hack that I've been recommending to
literally all of my friends
and about half of them have done it
and they've said oh my God this was game changing
and it's gonna sound weird but that is to do a
DEXA scan
and a DEXA scan is basically a full body X ray
and in hospitals we use DEXA scans
to measure the bone density of patients
who might be having osteoprocess
but the really cool thing about a DEXA scan
is that it can tell you how much muscle you have
and also how much fat you have
and also the distribution of
the muscle and the fat around your body
first thing to say is that they are somewhat expensive
well you know it's about
$120 to get a DEXAS scan
depending on where you go
I personally think that is absolutely worth it
because any amount of money you can spend on your health
if it changes your behavior
will pay dividends further down the line
obviously you're milage may vary
depending on how much disposable income you have
but every single person that I recommended DEXA scan to
who has done the DEXA scan has been like
oh my god
this is the best money I have ever spent on my health
because within like 15 minutes the scan will tell you
where your body fat is
and you might think that you're pretty skinny
like I thought I was like in reasonable shape
but then turns out I was actually 25 percent body fat
and most of it was in the abdomen
it was in the visceral adiposed tissue
and it's the visceral adiposed tissue
that's most highly correlated with
cardiovascular disease and strokes and diabetes
and all of the bad things that can happen later in life
and so since doing that first scan
about a year and a half ago
I've now been doing DEXA scans about every six months
and it's been an amazing way of actually
tracking my progress in the gym
tracking my progress with weight loss
and seeing how the numbers are changing over time
and yeah you could use scales
and you could use those
body fat scales that you get in the gym
but those are never really accurate
so after my first DEXA scan
I realized I had all this adipost tissue
and so we made a plan to lose some weight
but then
six months later I found I did lose a lot of weight
but most of it was muscle
because I didn't have enough protein
and because I didn't work out enough
and then I was like oh my god like okay
I can literally see that I've lost about
two kg of muscle and only one kg of fat
that's kind of annoying
and then we made a plan based on that DEXA scan
and then six months later
I gained 1.5 kg of muscle
and lost 1.5 kg of fat which is very nice
and for me personally
I love the fact that I have access to these numbers
and I love the fact that the numbers don't lie
and just doing a DEXA scan every 6 months
has been the single most worthwhile expense
I've ever made for my health
if you're based in the UK
the company I use is Bodyscan
who've got a bunch of different places around London
if not just to search DEXA scan your location
and I'm sure you can find a place
but generally DEXA scans are absolutely sick
ok speaking of protein intake
because that first time around for the first six months
I didn't eat enough protein
and I also didn't work out enough
and I actually lost 2kg of muscle
what I realized is I need to automate my protein intake
the amount of protein you need depends massively on
who you ask where you look at the source
and there doesn't seem to be much of a consensus
in the scientific literature about it
The World Health Organization for example
says you need 0.83 grams of protein
per kilogram body weight per day
but most personal trainers
and fitness experts that I've spoken to say that
that is nowhere near enough
to actually build muscle
if you are trying to build muscle
and so for me
I'm roughly aiming for around 1.5 to 2
grams of protein per kilogram of body weight
and this is actually annoyingly hard to get in in my diet
because I tend to skip breakfast and then lunch and dinner
it's like I have to actively think about protein
but one thing that I started to do to
automate my protein intake again
based on advice from my fitness coach Dan Go
it's very simple it's basically to just
have a protein shake in the morning
and when I have a protein shake in the morning
I get at least 40 grams of protein
sometimes 50 depending on which product I use
and now it's way easier to hit my protein goal
because if I just have a 30 gram serving of protein for lunch
than a 30 gram serving of protein for dinner
that's like 110 grams
that's pretty reasonable
now the two different types of protein shake that I use
are firstly Huel
I use Huel Black 400 calories for 40 grams of protein in the morning
if I feel like making it
or if I'm on the go and I don't feel like making it
I'll use the Optimum Nutrition Pre made Protein Shake
which is 50 grams of protein for 300 calories which is quite nice
no affiliate relationship or anything with these brands
although Huel do sponsor some of the other videos on the channel
but they're not sponsoring this one so whatevs
but eversince I started automating my protein intake
by literally just having a shake first thing in the morning
I've actually been hitting my protein goals broadly
and I've seen that reflect on the DEXA scan you know
the scan I had a year after my first one showed
that I gained 1.5kg of muscle and
lost 1.5kg of fat
in those six months
I made an active effort to up my protein intake
all right next we come to the idea of flexibility and mobility
now I'm not at all very flexible
and not at all very mobile
but there have been some pretty reasonable studies
that show that if you do have a
baseline level of flexibility and mobility
it helps reduce the risk of injury when you exercising
which is always a good thing
and for example this metaanalysis
found that the benefits of stretching
in middle age to older adults
reduced arterial stiffness
heart rate and blood pressure
and improved vascular endothelial functioning
and so if stretching is good
for middle age to older adults
it's probably good for younger adults as well
now I've tried so many ways to incorporating
stretching into my life
but two of them have so far worked
the first one is that every now and then
I will randomly put on a stretching routine on YouTube
and my favorite channel for this is juice and Toya
who have great videos with stretch routines and things like that
so that's great
in particular I love their routines for
tight hamstrings and hip flexors
which are the two areas I struggle with most
and recently I've also started using an app called pliability
again like no relationship with this app at all
they do not know I exist
but if pliability if you're watching this let me know
but basically it's an app that every day
just gives you a stretching routine to do
and it's like a 20 minute thing
that I do in the evening
and just roll out my Lululemon yoga mat
and for 20 minutes before bed I just prop my phone up
and it's like nice because it's very static stretches
it's like you're in each pose
and you're just holding it passively for like
three minutes at a time
and this nice relaxing music
and the production value is nice
and they occasionally have
dogs and stuff that go into the frame
and it's a very nice way to wind down for the evening
so it sort of doubles as a bit of a meditative thing as well
as well because I can help switch my mind off
but then it's also helping me improve my flexibility
and mobility through these sort of passive stretches
that don't take much effort
all right the penultimate hack is one of these
so I used to really struggle with
actually being consistent with taking my pills
I take a couple of supplements
I take the Heights Smart supplement
which is a big multivitamin thing
that has like blueberries and stuff
and take the Heights Smart Probiotic
which is a probiotic
and I take a couple of bits of medication
like Finasteride and minoxidil for my hair loss
but I would always be very inconsistent in taking these
because it wasn't built into my routine
until I realized that
you know when I was working as a doctor
we would give these
dosette boxes to our patients
and it would help them take their pills
and so I just thought one day
I'm just gonna buy one of these from Amazon
and so I bought one of these from Amazon and now
it helps me stay consistent with
taking my pills which is fantastic
so if you take any supplements or pills or anything
and you're having to bring them up manually
it's such a faff
it's so nice just being able to once a week
just fill this up for the whole week
and as I know
I forgot to take them yesterday
because even though I still forget sometimes
but today's Friday
I took them today this morning
and then the final hack is my
productive and evidence based skincare routine
this basically involves just three products
I've talked to a bunch of dermatologists
and this is broadly the stuff that they recommend
and I've got all the details about that
in this video over here
which is my evidence based skincare routine
so if you're interested then do check that video out
and I promise it will change
the way you approach your skincare routine
so thank you so much for watching
and I'll see you in the next video bye bye